Guide to the John A. Coke Papers (Records of the Confederate army enrolling office for the Third Congressional District of Virginia) 1861-1865 MS670.6
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
John A. Coke Papers (Records of the Confederate army enrolling office for the Third Congressional District of Virginia)
1861-1865
MS670.6
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
1.6 Linear feet (4 boxes)
This collection contains correspondence and official documents relating to John A. Coke's work as the enrolling officer for the Confederate army in the Third Congressional District of Virginia, headquartered in Richmond, Virginia. It includes papers relating to enrollment, conscription, exemptions, substitutes, detail assignments, and other documents concerning the availability of men for service in the Confederate army. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Coke, John Archer, 1842-1920
Biographical/Historical note
John Archer Coke was born in Williamsburg, Virginia, on July 14, 1842. In the years preceding the Civil War, he attended William and Mary College, graduating in 1860. In March, 1861, he enlisted in the Lee Artillery, an organization formed at Williamsburg, under Captain W.R. Garrett. Initially elected second lieutenant of the unit, Coke was subsequently promoted to captain. In 1862, Captain Coke was re-assigned to duty as enrolling officer for the Third Congressional District of Virginia, with headquarters at Richmond, under command of Col. John C. Shields, commander of the Conscript Department of Virginia (later replaced by General J.L. Kemper).
As enrolling officer, Coke was charged with enforcing the conscription law passed by the Confederate Congress on April 16, 1862. The first conscription law in American history (preceding the Union draft by nearly a year), the Confederate act drafted all white males between 18 and 35 for a three-year term of service. In September 1862, as southern casualties mounted, the conscription age was raised to 45, and by February 1864, the limits were 17 and 50.
Exemptions were provided for certain occupations considered to be vital to the war effort, such as railroad workers, miners, telegraph operators, and druggists. More controversially, the "Twenty-Negro law" allowed the owner or overseer of a plantation with 20 or more slaves to avoid army service. Wealthy southerners were also permitted to hire substitutes to take their place in the army. These exemptions were widely resented as belonging to "a rich man's war and a poor man's fight," and were both eventually abolished in the face of increasing manpower shortages.
Coke remained at his position until Richmond was evacuated, at which point he accompanied General Kemper, with a party of other officers, to Halifax County. Hearing of Lee's surrender, the party attempted to join General Johnston's army. When Johnston also surrendered, Coke returned to Danville, Virginia, and gave his parole to the Federal authorities.
Returning home to Williamsburg, Coke studied law and in September, 1865, opened a law practice in Richmond. In 1867, he married Emma Overbey, with whom he had several children. He died January 27, 1920.
Conditions governing access
Open to qualified researchers.
Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Items that include presidential signatures will be presented to researchers in duplicate form.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of correspondence and official papers relating to Captain John Archer Coke's work as enrolling officer for the Confederate army in the Third Congressional District of Virginia. The papers concern enrollment, exemptions, substitutes, work details, partially disabled soldiers on limited service, senior reserves, deserters and other absentees from active units, conscription policies, and the availability of men for the Confederate army from Richmond, Hanover, Charles City, Henrico, Charles City, James City, York, and New Kent Counties.
Documents include individual applications for exemptions, correspondence, general and special orders issued and received, circulars and regulations, conscription reports and lists from each county, and papers relating to substitutes, deserters, manpower for essential industry, senior reserves, and details for men on limited service. Of particular interest are conscription reports and detail assignments for "free negroes." There are also documents relating to the Mounted Guards (employed by the conscription office to execute the conscription law) and to the internal operations of the conscription office.
The collection has been arranged into series by county. Series I, Richmond County/District-wide Records, includes enrollment records from Richmond County (headquarters for the Third Congressional District), as well as documents relating to District-wide enrollment policies and procedures. Enrollment records from the other counties of the Third Congressional District (Hanover, Charles City, Henrico, Charles City, James City, York, and New Kent) are found in Series II and III. Within each series, documents have been organized by type.
The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Sources
Evans, Clement A. (1899). Confederate Military History; a library of Confederate states history. Atlanta, Ga: Confederate Pub. Co.
Arrangement note
This collection has been organized into the following three series:
Series I. Richmond County/District-wide Records
Series II. Hanover County Records
Series III: Records of other counties within the Third Congressional District
Confederate States of America. Army.
- Series I: Richmond County/District-wide Records
  - Inspection Office Reports, 1863 March, 1863 December, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and receipts, 1862 October - 1864 December, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Endorsement book, 1864 August - 1865 April (Box OS Small, Folder Coke, John A.)
  - Military orders, 1862 March - 1865 July (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Special orders of Enrolling Office, 1864 April 12 - 1864 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Regulations and circulars, 1861 October 20, 1863 March - 1864 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Book recording circulars (Box OS Small, Folder Coke, John A.)
  - Lists and accounts of Mounted Conscription Guards and others serving in the conscription office, 1863 August - 1864 December, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Muster rolls of Mounted Conscription Guard and other enrollment office personnel, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Monthly reports -- Nominal (lists of conscripts, deserters, etc.), 1863 March - 1864 October, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Statistical reports, 1863 November - 1865 January, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Daily enrollment lists, 1862 December - 1864 October (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Enrollment and descriptive lists of reservists, 1864 April (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Lists of men in the 19th and 179th Regiments, Virginia Militia, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lists of details and exemptions, 1861 - 1863 October, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - List of details and exemptions December, 1862, 1862 December (Box OS Small, Folder Coke, John A.)
  - Detail orders and conscription reports of free African Americans, 1864 April - 1864 October, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reports of deserters, 1862 October - 1863 September (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Register of all men not serving with the Army, 1864 September (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Book recording detail assignments and exemptions, 1862 December - 1863 November (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Book recording reports of absentees and deserters, 1864 May - 1864 October (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Requests for exemption and other documents relating to individual conscription status, 1861 September - 1865 March, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Exemption certificates, 1862 December - 1864 August (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Printed forms (blank) (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series II: Hanover County Records
  - Nominal and statistical reports, 1863 May - 1865 January, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Requests for exemption and other documents related to individual conscription status, 1862 August - 1864 September, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lists and accounts of Mounted Conscription Guards, 1864 May, 1865 February, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series III: Records of other counties within the Third Congressional District
  - Charles City County Records, 1863 September - 1865 January, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Henrico County Records, 1863 March - 1865 February, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - James City and York County Records, 1860 December - 1863 July (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - New Kent County Records, 1863 January - 1865 January, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)